<tool id="vcf_filtering_depth" name="VCF masking : min and maximum depth" version="0.1.0" python_template_version="3.5">
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="package" version="1.23">bcftools</requirement>
    </requirements>

    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        mkdir -p vcf_filtered_directory &&

        bash '$__tool_directory__/vcf_filtering_depth.sh'
            '${vcf_input}'
            '${vcf_input.element_identifier}'
            '$MIN_DP'

        ]]></command>
    
    <inputs>
        <param name="vcf_input" type="data" format="vcf" label="Upload your VCF file"
            help="File containing DNA sequence data in VCF format. You can upload a simple file, multiple files or a dataset collection." />

        <param name="MIN_DP" type="integer" value="6" min="1" label="Minimum read depth (MIN_DP)"
            help="Minimum read depth (DP) per genotype required to retain it. 
            Typical values depend on sequencing coverage: 1–5 for permissive filtering, 10–20 for standard filtering, and ≥30 for stringent filtering." />
    </inputs>

    <outputs>
        <data name="vcf_filtered" format="vcf" label="${tool.name}">
            <discover_datasets pattern="(?P&lt;designation&gt;.+)\.vcf$" directory="vcf_filtered_directory" visible="true" assign_primary_output="true"/>
        </data>
    </outputs>

    <tests>
        <test>
            <param name="vcf_input" value="test_vcf.vcf"/>
            <param name="MIN_DP" value="6"/>
            <output name="vcf_filtered" file="vcf_filtered_directory/test_vcf_DP.vcf" count="1"/>
        </test>
    </tests>

        <help><![CDATA[
Usage
=====
As input, the user provides one or more VCF files (Danecek *et al.* 2011) and a threshold value indicating a minimum read depth. 

For each input VCF file, the tool replaces genotype calls with missing values (./.) if their depth (DP) is less than the user-defined minimum or exceeds a maximum threshold (automatically calculated as twice the average depth observed in the data file).

The tool automatically detects whether DP is stored in the INFO/DP or FORMAT/DP field of the VCF file. If no DP annotation is found, the input and output VCF files are identical.

Example: If the average depth in a VCF data file is 30 and the user sets a minimum threshold of 5, any genotype with DP < 5 or DP > 60 is considered missing data and masked.

Tips
====
The threshold values for minimum read depth depend on the objectives of the study. 
The minimum threshold is generally greater than 5 in order to avoid underestimating certain statistics, such as observed and expected heterozygosity (Kardos and Waples, 2024).

See also examples of VCF formats in :  https://samtools.github.io/hts-specs/VCFv4.5.pdf

    ]]></help>

    <citations>
        <citation type="bibtex">
        @article{10.1093/gigascience/giab008,
    author = {Danecek, Petr and Bonfield, James K and Liddle, Jennifer and Marshall, John and Ohan, Valeriu and Pollard, Martin O and Whitwham, Andrew and Keane, Thomas and McCarthy, Shane A and Davies, Robert M and Li, Heng},
    title = "{Twelve years of SAMtools and BCFtools}",
    journal = {GigaScience},
    volume = {10},
    number = {2},
    year = {2021},
    abstract = "{SAMtools and BCFtools are widely used programs for processing and analysing high-throughput sequencing data. They include tools for file format conversion and manipulation, sorting, querying, statistics, variant calling, and effect analysis amongst other methods.The first version appeared online 12 years ago and has been maintained and further developed ever since, with many new features and improvements added over the years. The SAMtools and BCFtools packages represent a unique collection of tools that have been used in numerous other software projects and countless genomic pipelines.Both SAMtools and BCFtools are freely available on GitHub under the permissive MIT licence, free for both non-commercial and commercial use. Both packages have been installed \\&gt;1 million times via Bioconda. The source code and documentation are available from https://www.htslib.org.}",
    issn = {2047-217X},
    doi = {10.1093/gigascience/giab008},
    url = {https://doi.org/10.1093/gigascience/giab008},
    note = {giab008},
    eprint = {https://academic.oup.com/gigascience/article-pdf/10/2/giab008/36332246/giab008.pdf},
        }
        </citation>
        <citation type="bibtex">
            @article{Kardos2025LowCoverageWolves,
  author  = {Kardos, Molly and Waples, Robin S.},
  title   = {Low-coverage sequencing and Wahlund effect severely bias estimates of inbreeding, heterozygosity and effective population size in North American wolves},
  journal = {Molecular Ecology},
  year    = {2025},
  volume  = {34},
  number  = {20},
  pages   = {e17415},
  doi     = {10.1111/mec.17415},
}

        </citation>
        <citation type="bibtex">
            @article{Danecek2011,
  author          = {Danecek, Petr and Auton, Adam and Abecasis, Goncalo and Albers, Cornelis A. and Banks, Erica and DePristo, Mark A. and Handsaker, Robert E. and Lunter, Gerton and Marth, Gabor T. and Sherry, Stephen T. and McVean, Gil and Durbin, Richard and {1000 Genomes Project Analysis Group}},
  title           = {The variant call format and {VCF}tools},
  journal         = {Bioinformatics},
  volume          = {27},
  number          = {15},
  pages           = {2156-2158},
  year            = {2011},
  doi             = {10.1093/bioinformatics/btr330},
  URL             = {https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btr330},
  eprint          = {https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article-pdf/27/15/2156/600788/btr330.pdf},
}
        </citation>
    <citation type="bibtex">
        @manual{VCFv45,
  title        = {The Variant Call Format (VCF) Specification, Version 4.5},
  author       = {{HTS-specs team}},
  organization = {Global Alliance for Genomics and Health},
  year         = {2024},
  url          = {https://samtools.github.io/hts-specs/VCFv4.5.pdf},
  note         = {Accessed: 2025-02-11}
}
    </citation>
    </citations>
</tool>